Guide to the Gil J Wolman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1950-1995; Series III; 12.69; (27 boxes)
  - Books, 1960-1995
    - Peinture dépeinte
      - Excerpt ["Apparition connue inconnue…"], autograph manuscript and printout, [1992] (Box 23, Folder 349)
      - Drafts titled "Manuscrits Juin 93 Les Inhumations", autograph manuscript, 1993-06- (Box 23, Folder 350-353)
      - Notebooks titled "Manuscrits Juin 93 Les Inhumations", autograph, 1993-06- (Box 24, Folder 354-360)
        Untitled notebooks with drafts for various chronological segments of Peinture dépeinte.
      - Notebooks, autograph, circa 1994 (Box 24, Folder 361-362)
      - Printout "Suite du journal d'une exposition", [1991] (Box 24, Folder 363)
        Peinture dépeinte text for 1991 February 18 to 1991 September 07.
      - Excerpt for 1994 January-February, printout with pasted oval shapes (Box 24, Folder 364)
      - Excerpt for 1994 October - 1995 May, printout (Box 25, Folder 365)
      - Les inhumations, ceci n'est pas un livre (Éditions inconnues), printout with autograph corrections, undated (Box 25, Folder 366-367)
      - Les inhumations, followed by Peinture dépeinte, printout, undated (Box 25, Folder 368)
      - Les inhumations (Éditions inconnues), bound typescript, [1994] (Box 25, Folder 369)
      - Les inhumations, suivi de Peinture dépeinte (Éditions Allia), cover design and erratum, 1995- (Box 25, Folder 370)
      - Unpublished sequel "Mars 1995 suite des Inhumations", printouts, 1995-03- (Box 25, Folder 371)
        - Fragile item on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 806)
    - Le sens perdu de l'interruption, paste-ups and proofs, [1987] (Box 25, Folder 372-375)
    - Quelques jours en août, affiches restaurées, typescripts of French and Italian texts, [1976] (Box 26, Folder 376-377)
      For a portfolio containing copies of the French affiches exhibited at Galerie Weiller (1977), see Series VI., Box 59, Folder 761-762.
    - Vivre et mourir, précédé par introduction et séparation du mot
      - Draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1984 (Box 26, Folder 378)
      - Bound typescript with annotations, circa 1984 (Box 26, Folder 379)
      - Bound typescript, circa 1984 (Box 26, Folder 380)
      - Material for dedication, circa 1984 (Box 26, Folder 381)
    - Wolman résumé des chapitres précédents
      - Background material file ("Documents originaux"), circa 1960-1980 (Box 27, Folder 382-386)
        Includes correspondence and ephemera related to exhibitions, and a typescript of the 1968 radio program "Beyond the Word" by Simon Watson Taylor on sound poetry.
      - Background material file ("Wolman / Art scotch / Séparation / Manifestation"), circa 1960-1980 (Box 27, Folder 387-390)
        Includes newspaper clippings and articles.
      - Background material file, circa 1960-1980 (Box 28, Folder 391-396)
        - Oversize items (Box 60 (Oversize), Folder 769-770)
        - Oversize items (Box 61 (Oversize), Folder 778-779)
        - Fragile documents on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 807)
      - Paste-up with autograph additions, circa 1981 (Box 28, Folder 397-403)
      - Unbound proofs, circa 1981 (Box 29, Folder 404-414)
        - Oversize unbound proofs, circa 1981 (Box 62 (Oversize), Folder 783-785)
      - Bound proof, circa 1981 (Box 30, Folder 415)
      - Cover maquette, circa 1981 (Box 30, Folder 416)
      - Pages selected for the exhibition I am immortal and alive, Museu d'Art Contemporani de Barcelona, 2010- (Box 30, Folder 417)
      - "Wolman résumé of the preceding chapters", typescript, undated (Box 30, Folder 418)
    - Wolman résumé sequel preparation
      - "Wolman résumé", curriculum vitae until 1987, typescript, circa 1987 (Box 30, Folder 419)
      - Background material file "1981" (Box 30, Folder 420)
      - Background material file "1982" (Box 30, Folder 421-422)
        - "1982" oversize materials (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 745)
      - Background material file "1983" (Box 30, Folder 423-424)
      - Background material file "1984" (Box 30, Folder 425-426)
      - Background material file "1985" (Box 30, Folder 427-428)
      - Background material file "1986" (Box 31, Folder 429)
      - Background material file "1987" (Box 31, Folder 430)
      - Background material file "1988" (Box 31, Folder 431)
      - Background material file "1989" (Box 31, Folder 432)
  - Short Works, 1950-1990
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Adaptation of Albert Camus' L'étranger for theater, autograph manuscript, circa 1950 (Box 32, Folder 433)
    - "L'autre moitié", printouts in large font, undated (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 746)
    - "Big omelette", printout, circa 1990 (Box 32, Folder 434)
    - Commentary on the Artists Anonymous manifesto, with Ralph Rumney, drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, circa 1969 (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 747)
    - "Exclusion manifeste", drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, [1988] (Box 32, Folder 435)
    - "Exclusion manifeste", drafts, typescript with autograph corrections, 1987-1988 (Box 32, Folder 436)
      File of typescripts originally grouped together, accompanied by the holograph note "Hors Texte de la série Je suis la proie des mots 1987-1988".
    - "Il faut dire l'art-non", autograph manuscript and printed maquette, undated (Box 32, Folder 437)
    - "J'écris propre", typescript with autograph corrections, [1956] (Box 32, Folder 438)
      - Fragile originals (Box 66, Folder 808)
    - "Je garde mon jeu" / "Proefari", typed cards, undated (Box 32, Folder 439)
    - "Journal d'une exposition", printouts in large font, circa 1988 (Box 32, Folder 440-441)
      This text was included in Wolman's anthology De l'anticoncept à l'anticoncept (Paris: Éditions inconnues, 1990).
    - "La nuit n'est pas un endroit pour mourir", screenplay, autograph manuscript, 1971-09-25- (Box 32, Folder 442)
    - "Sur le temps qu'il faut de l'interruption volontaire à l'image" and other texts, printouts, undated (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 748)
      Original grouping also containing printouts of the texts "Je suis la proie des mots les mots m'écrivent", "Le livre des mots", and "Comment taire le tableau".
  - Early Lettrist Writings, 1950-1964
    - ["Ils étaient traités d'hérétiques.."], notes on the Lettrist movement, circa 1964 (Box 32, Folder 443)
    - "Improvisations mégapneumes" and theoretical writings on art intégral, circa 1950 (Box 32, Folder 444)
    - "Lettre à Guy Ernest Debord sur les formes propres de l'esthétique[…]", autograph notebook, 1952-12-10- (Box 32, Folder 445)
      Notebook containing five pages titled "Lettre à Guy Ernest Debord sur les formes propres de l'esthétique et de la situation, les glissements spécifiques de découvertes concommittantes et de la théorie wolmanienne de l'homme seul", dated 1952 December 10, with annotations in another hand. The notebook also contains two pages of notes regarding Le front de la jeunesse.
    - Lettrist poems file, circa 1952 (Box 32, Folder 446)
      File of autograph manuscript poems originally grouped together that includes several fragments with missing text.
    - ["La mégapneumie prend possession de chacun des signes des lettres…"], theoretical note, circa 1953 (Box 32, Folder 447)
    - Notations for mégapneumes, circa 1951 (Box 33, Folder 448)
    - Notes on art intégral, circa 1950 (Box 33, Folder 449)
      - Fragile original (Box 66, Folder 809)
    - Notes file on mégapneumie, circa 1951 (Box 33, Folder 450)
      - Fragile originals (Box 66, Folder 810)
    - Notes file on mégapneumie, circa 1951 (Box 33, Folder 451-452)
    - Notebook "La mégapneumie", circa 1951 (Box 33, Folder 453)
    - Notebook with notations and drawings, circa 1950 (Box 33, Folder 454)
    - Notebook on language, circa 1950 (Box 33, Folder 455)
    - Notebook on theater and phonetics, circa 1950 (Box 33, Folder 456)
      - Fragile original notebook (Box 66, Folder 811)
    - "Pourquoi je ne participe pas à l'exposition lettrisme et hypergraphie", draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1964 (Box 33, Folder 457)
    - Untitled draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1950 (Box 33, Folder 458)
  - Notes and Untitled Manuscripts, 1950-1990
    Arranged alphabetically. Incipits, indicated by the symbols ["..."], are provided in the absence of title information.
    - ["L'art est un jeu d'émigrant …"], poem, typescript, undated (Box 33, Folder 459)
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 812)
    - ["Ce n'est pas tant de le dire…"], note, autograph, undated (Box 33, Folder 460)
    - ["C'est le blanc qui limite…"]/["La couleur c'est l'espace incontrolé…"], poems, typescript, circa 1990 (Box 33, Folder 461)
    - ["Cette lumière qui se soulève…"], fragment, autograph, undated (Box 33, Folder 462)
    - ["Commence l'endroit…"], fragment, autograph, undated (Box 33, Folder 463)
    - "Le commentaire" file containing untitled drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 33, Folder 464)
    - ["Doit-on dire le bonheur…"], poem, printout, 1989- (Box 33, Folder 465)
    - "Hôtel des Marronniers 22 novembre 1988", notebook, autograph, 1988-11-22- (Box 33, Folder 466)
      One page with holograph text. Rest of notebook is empty.
    - ["-Intellectuel! Je décrocherai ma droite…"], fragment, autograph, circa 1955-1960 (Box 33, Folder 467)
      The text was published posthumously in Défense de mourir, edited by Gérard Berréby (Paris: Éditions Allia, 2001).
    - ["Je n'ai pas d'idées..."], fragment, autograph, undated (Box 33, Folder 468)
    - "Manuscrits, chansons, écrits" file, undated (Box 33, Folder 469-470)
    - "No change", poem, printout, undated (Box 33, Folder 471)
    - ["Notation de l'inaudible…"], draft, typescript, undated (Box 34, Folder 472-473)
      The text was published posthumously in Défense de mourir, edited by Gérard Berréby (Paris: Éditions Allia, 2001), under the devised title "Joseph me voilà".
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 66, Folder 813)
    - ["Trouver un mot passe encore…"], autograph text on cards, undated (Box 34, Folder 474)
    - Notes on François Dufrêne and Wolman, 1975 and undated (Box 34, Folder 475)
      Contains an excerpt transcribed in Wolman's hand of a 1975 interview with Dufrêne on Poésie interrompue, France Culture, in which Dufrêne discusses Wolman's mégapneumes; and three pages of notes "À propos de Dufrêne (son appartenance de plusieurs mois au groupe isouien".
    - Notes on recording, undated (Box 34, Folder 476)
    - Notes, miscellaneous, circa 1950-1990 (Box 34, Folder 477)
    - Notebook on Israel, circa 1950 (Box 34, Folder 478)
    - Notebooks with autograph drafts, possibly relating to Les entrepôts d'Ivry, circa 1986 (Box 34, Folder 479)
    - Notepad with autograph drafts, [1994] (Box 34, Folder 480)
    - Notebook, blank, undated (Box 34, Folder 481)
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, undated (Box 35, Folder 482)
      Possibly a film sequence plan.
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, undated (Box 35, Folder 483)
      Includes autograph text ["On nous vante la civilisation…"].
    - Untitled manuscripts, file including a screenplay, 1953-circa 1990 (Box 35, Folder 484-487)
      Includes an autograph draft, and a typescript with corrections dated 1953 May 31, for an untitled screenplay in five parts. Incipit: ["Cette fille est nue, sa peau noire"]. The script was published posthumously in Défense de mourir, edited by Gérard Berréby (Paris: Éditions Allia, 2001), under the devised title "Joseph me voilà". The file also includes later autograph drafts ["Il faut dire quelque chose.."], ["À la fin des années 40 quand j'étais lettriste…"], and "Sans suite"; and typescripts "De la dil à la dil", "À ma rive étallée", and "Schema de mes formes tuées".
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1978-1990 (Box 35, Folder 488)
      Includes the typescript "Constat d'échec du 20 septembre 1978", an autograph excerpt from "La séparation du mot", and a note "Le lettrisme n'est pas le lettrisme".
    - Untitled manuscripts, file about séparation, 1979-1988 (Box 35, Folder 489)
      Autograph texts and fragments, mostly relating to Wolman's concept of séparation. Includes "La séparation des corps" (dated 1981 June 12), "Mouvement séparatiste" (undated), "Lettre ouverte" (circa 1988), and "Projection ou le concept retrouvé, un film de GW" (dated 1988 May 31).
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1991 (Box 35, Folder 490)
      Includes the autograph and typed texts ["La création est un jeu d'enfants…"] and ["Plus j'approche de moi plus j'éloigne l'autre"].
    - Untitled manuscripts and photocopies, file, undated (Box 35, Folder 491-492)
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, undated (Box 35, Folder 493)
      Includes the typescript text ["Le moi l'émotion le mot…"].
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1955-1988 (Box 36, Folder 494)
      Includes autograph texts and fragments, and the short typescripts ["Il découpe ses tableaux selon l'art des pointillés…"], "Projection ou le concept retrouvé", ["Il faut inventer la nature…"], "Je garde mon jeu", and ["Viv es un évid…"].
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1970-1990 (Box 36, Folder 495)
      Contains several short autograph texts, including "Le conte à rebours", ["De l'arbre / merveilleuse tenue…"], ["Il y avait un grand front populaire…"], ["Le simple mot de géométrie…"], and ["-Il fait nuit…"].
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1980-1985 (Box 36, Folder 496)
      Contains autograph and typed pages, including "Wolman par Wolman", "Wolman par les autres", "À propos d'une exposition qui n'aura pas lieu", and "Un an après".
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1975-1990 (Box 36, Folder 497-498)
      Includes the autograph texts "Quelques minutes de la vie d'un homme", "Histoire de Monsieur Pipe", and ["Les hommes sont ce qu'ils sont..."], and the typescripts ["Silence…"] and ["Il y a loin…"]. Also includes autograph fragments related to Wolman's concept of séparation.
    - Untitled manuscripts, file, circa 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 499)
      Includes typescripts of poems and autograph fragments.
    - Untitled printouts, file, undated (Box 57 (Oversize), Folder 749)
- L'Anticoncept Film Files, 1951-2000; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Series IV. contains screenplay drafts, essays, invoices, ephemera, clippings, and other materials related to Wolman's experimental film L'Anticoncept. A landmark of Lettrist cinema created in 1951, the film solely consists of a sound track narrated by Wolman and images of white circles projected on a balloon. After its first screening in February 1952 in Paris, the film was censored by the French authorities in April 1952, and showed only to journalists at the 1952 Cannes Film Festival. Materials in Series IV. date from the film's original conception and screenings in the early 1950s, and from the 1980s-1990s, documenting a resurgence of interest in screening Wolman's work as part of avant-garde cinema retrospectives.
  Arranged alphabetically by document type.
  See Series I. for correspondence from cultural institutions and production companies regarding L'Anticoncept. See Series VII., Box 52, Folder 690 for the film's sound track on phonograph record.
  Box 67: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Envelope labels, undated (Box 37, Folder 500)
    - Original envelopes (Box 67, Folder 814)
  - L'Anticoncept (Éditions Allia, 1994), proofs of published screenplay, circa 1994 (Box 37, Folder 501)
  - Censorship notice from the Commission de contrôle des films cinématographiques, 1952- (Box 37, Folder 502)
    - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 815)
  - Certificate from the Centre national de la cinématographie - conservation du registre public, 1952-03- (Box 37, Folder 503)
    - Fragile original (Box 67, Folder 816)
  - Clippings, 1995- (Box 37, Folder 504)
    - Oversize clipping, 1995 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 750)
    - Fragile clipping (Box 67, Folder 817)
  - Designs for title page, [1952] (Box 37, Folder 505)
    - Fragile originals (Box 67, Folder 818)
  - Essay "La lumière (L'Anticoncept)", draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1952 (Box 37, Folder 506)
    Initial draft for "Le cinematochrone nouvelle amplitude".
  - Essay "Le cinematochrone nouvelle amplitude", draft, typescript, circa 1952 (Box 37, Folder 507)
  - Essay "Le mouvement et le rapport de l'artiste, de son film aux spectateurs", draft, typescript, undated (Box 37, Folder 508)
  - Essay "Pour un art de l'anticoncept", draft, autograph manuscript, circa 1990 (Box 37, Folder 509)
  - Film strips, circa 1951 (Box 37, Folder 510)
    Contains one 35mm film strip of 30 cm in length, and a photographic print of another 35mm film fragment.
  - Flyers and programs for screenings, 1952-2000 (Box 37, Folder 511)
  - Interview by Nicolas Villodre, 1989- (Box 37, Folder 512)
    Two page typescript with corrections of interview with Wolman about the film, in preparation for its presentation at the Centre Georges Pompidou in 1989.
  - Invoice for broadcasting rights, 1994- (Box 37, Folder 513)
    - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 819)
  - Invoices for screenings, 1951- (Box 37, Folder 514)
  - List of films censored in France, photocopy, undated (Box 37, Folder 515)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 37, Folder 516)
  - Petition again censorship signed by J.A. Ramos and E.A. Carvallo, circa 1952 (Box 37, Folder 517)
  - Postcards by La Galerie de Poche, undated (Box 37, Folder 518)
    Eleven numbered copies.
  - Press release for Centre Georges Pompidou screening, [1981] (Box 37, Folder 519)
  - Printed tract "Pourquoi les spectateurs hurleront pendant la projection de L'Anticoncept ", circa 1952 (Box 37, Folder 520)
  - Printed tract "La technique ne décide pas de tout", undated (Box 37, Folder 521)
    - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 820)
  - Screenplay, autograph manuscript, circa 1951 (Box 38, Folder 522)
  - Screenplay, autograph fragment, circa 1951 (Box 38, Folder 523)
    - Fragile originals (Box 67, Folder 821)
  - Screenplay (first page missing), draft, typescript with autograph corrections, circa 1951 (Box 38, Folder 524)
    - Fragile originals (Box 67, Folder 822)
  - Screenplay, "Tapuscripts L'Anticoncept", file, circa 1951 (Box 38, Folder 525-528)
    Contains two complete typed copies with annotations, and fragments of other screenplays and texts by Wolman.
  - Screenplay, drafts, typescript, circa 1951 (Box 38, Folder 529)
  - Screenplay, proofs and printing tests for publication in Ion, no. 1, [1952] (Box 38, Folder 530-531)
    Also contains proofs for Serge Berna, "Jusqu'à l'os", published in the same issue.
- Professional Papers, 1952-2008; Series V; 2.93; (8 boxes)
  Organized into four subseries: Administrative Documents, Exhibition and Trade Publications, Ephemera, and Editorial Work.
  Series V. documents Wolman's presence in the Paris art scene from the 1960s to the 1990s through his gallery shows, his participation to collective exhibitions, art fairs, and festivals, and his editorial work for the directory L'Officiel des galleries. The series also illustrates interest in Wolman's work outside of Paris by a few cultural institutions across France, Europe, and North America. Administrative documents in the series largely relate to exhibition preparation, and include loan receipts, forms, and project proposals. Publications and printed ephemera include catalogs from museum exhibitions, gallery shows, art fairs, and auction sales featuring Wolman's art or other artists in his network; and invitation cards, posters, and flyers advertising his gallery shows. The series also includes a small group of material relating to Wolman's editorial work for three cultural magazines published in Paris: L'Entracte, L'Officiel des antiquaries, and L'Officiel des galleries.
  - Administrative Documents, 1952-1995
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Film festival passes, 1952-1982 (Box 39, Folder 532)
    - Galerie Florence Houston Brown receipts, 1963- (Box 39, Folder 533)
    - Constitution for the Société anonyme de beaux arts (SABA), circa 1965 (Box 39, Folder 534)
    - Maison de la Culture du Havre loan receipts, 1966-1967 (Box 39, Folder 535)
    - Salon Comparaisons forms and exhibitor card, 1967-1972 (Box 39, Folder 536)
    - Maison de la Culture de Grenoble loan receipts, 1969-1976 (Box 39, Folder 537)
    - Salon des réalités nouvelles deposit certificate, 1972-1973 (Box 39, Folder 538)
    - École supérieure des sciences économiques et commerciales exhibition preparation, 1974- (Box 39, Folder 539)
    - Foire internationale d'art contemporain (F.I.A.C.) installation preparation, 1974-1987 (Box 39, Folder 540-544)
      Contains project descriptions, forms, and calls for public participation in creating Wolman's F.I.A.C. installations. Includes typescripts for "Projet pour le PIAC (Parking International d'Art Contemporain)" (1977) and "Dispersion de la collection Wolman" [circa 1982]; a press release and delivery forms for the installation of fax machines for "Je vous envoie un dessin" (1984); a call for photograph submissions for "L'autre moitié" (1986); and holograph price list for several artists (1987). Accompanied by the tract "Intervention no. 2 L'oreille de Van Gogh" (1974) by Henri J. Enu for the 1975 F.I.A.C.
    - Ville de Bellême, Artistes en liberté dans le Perche participant dossier, 1977- (Box 39, Folder 545)
      Accompanied by clippings documenting the event.
      - Oversize maps and clippings of Bellême, 1977 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 751)
      - Original newspaper clippings (Box 67, Folder 824-825)
    - "Avis de recherche" for portrait pieces, 1978- (Box 39, Folder 546)
    - Salon de Mai exhibitor card, 1979- (Box 39, Folder 547)
    - Seconde Modernité, Color exhibition preparation, 1993- (Box 39, Folder 548)
      Contract, project proposal, clipping, and letter from Jacques Spiess regarding the organization of the New York exhibition Color, based on the French exhibition Nouvelle pigmentation.
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 826)
    - Fonds national d'art contemporain, artist profile form, 1993- (Box 39, Folder 549)
      Accompanied by a Fonds d'incitation à la création application checklist.
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 827)
    - Centre Georges Pompidou, Hors limites exhibition preparation, 1994- (Box 39, Folder 550-551)
      Loan forms, insurance forms, photocopy of Wolman's "J'écris propre" collage loaned to the Centre Pompidou, and correspondence related to the exhibition.
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 828)
    - Centre Georges Pompidou, Voir de mémoire exhibition preparation, 1995- (Box 39, Folder 552)
    - Musée de Marseille exhibition space plan, undated (Box 39, Folder 553)
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 829)
    - "Les Américains" project proposal, undated (Box 39, Folder 554)
    - Curriculum vitae, typescript, undated (Box 39, Folder 555)
    - Miscellaneous invoices, circa 1968-1992 (Box 39, Folder 556)
      - Fragile original on thermal paper (Box 67, Folder 823)
  - Exhibition and Trade Publications, 1960-2008
    - Festival d'art d'avant-garde program, 1960- (Box 40, Folder 557)
    - Salon Comparaisons catalogs, 1962-1976 (Box 40, Folder 558-562)
      Catalogs for the years 1962, 1968, 1972, 1974, and 1976.
    - Musée d'art moderne de Paris, Exposition internationale du petit bronze catalog, 1962- (Box 40, Folder 563-564)
      Accompanied by the flyer for Wolman's sculpture "Hypothétique manifeste de l'hypothétisme".
    - Musée d'art moderne de Paris, Biennale de Paris catalog and calendars, 1963-1965 (Box 40, Folder 565-566)